Guide to the Poles in Western Pennsylvania Collection, 1910s-1990s AIS.1965.16
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Poles in Western Pennsylvania Collection
1950s-1990s
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Borkowski, Joseph A.
AIS.1965.16
26.5 Linear Feet (20 record boxes and 3 manuscript boxes)
Material documenting Polish Americans in western Pennsylvania collected by Joseph A. Borkowski. A digital reproduction of the last issue of the Pittsburczanin can be accessed online (https://digital.library.pitt.edu/islandora/object/pitt:31735066257571).
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following nine series:
Series I. Poles in the United States and Western Pennsylvania
Series II. Societies
Series III. Borkowski, Joseph
Series IV. Individuals
Series V. Wars and Polish Veterans
Series VI. Programs, Events and Activities
Series VII. Publications and Books
Series VIII. Videotapes and Film
Series IX. Scrapbooks and Photo Albums
Previous Citation
Poles in Western Pennsylvania Collection, 1950s-1990s, AIS.1965.16, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Biography
Portions excerpted from Lawrenceville Historical Society: Joesph A. Borkowski.
Joseph A. Borkowski (1907-2003) dedicated his life to the preservation and fostering of interest in ethnic and local history. He received his elementary education at Immaculate Heart of Mary School and Holy Family, graduated from Duquesne University with a bachelor's degree in economics, and earned a master's degree in history at the University of Pittsburgh. He was employed by the city of Pittsburgh for 27 years as an auditor-accountant, supervisor of the parking tax department, and manager of wage tax. He also worked for the Allegheny County controller's office. He was World War II veteran who served in the African and Italian campaigns.
Acknowledged as the "unofficial" Polish historian of Pittsburgh, Borkowski was instrumental in obtaining a number of historical markers and plaques. These included ones honoring Anthony Sadowski (Allegheny County Court House), Polish Volunteers in American Civil War (City Council Building), Marcella Sembrich (William Penn Hotel on the corner of Oliver Ave. and Strawberry Way), Polish Army Recruitment (97 S. 18th St., site of old Falcon Hall), Three Polish Army Chaplains (Immaculate Heart of Mary Church), Casimir Pulaski's First Battle at Brandywine (marker on Highway #1 Chadd's Ford), Pulaski's Training and Recruitment Site (York, PA), Pulaski Banner Site (Bethlehem, PA), and Marie Sklodowska Curie (Graduate School, University of Pittsburgh, O'Hara St., Pittsburgh). The Polish prelate, Karol Cardinal Wojtyla, who would later become Pope John Paul II, dedicated the last plaque listed.
Borkowski was also instrumental in obtaining a plaque marking the 50th anniversary of the participation of American pilots in the Polish-Russian War. To obtain the markers, Borkowski, who served as Chairman of the Polish Historical Commission of the Central Council of Polish Organizations, researched and provided the necessary documentation. His writings included materials on Polish Pioneers of Pittsburgh; Anthony Sadowski; Christian Frederick Post; Marcella Sembrich; Madame Modrzejewska; Ignance Jan Paderewski's first Pittsburgh Concert; Stanislaus Parzyk, the first Polish priest in Pittsburgh; Pittsburgh's Part in the Formation of the Polish Army in France; History of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish and Cemetery; Madame Marie Sklodowska Curie's visit to Pittsburgh; History of Holy Family Parish; Colonial and Pre-Revolutionary Poles; and the Poles of Jamestown. It is unclear how many of these pieces were published and how many were submitted as required source documents.
As President of the Central Council of the Polish Organizations, Borkowski served as Master of Ceremonies when the United States Post Office issued a stamp in 1966 commemorating a thousand years of Christianity in Poland. He also initiated the Polish Christian Millennium at the Civic Arena, which drew over 20,000 people.
Shortly after the Lawrenceville Historical Society was organized in 1982, one of its first acts of business was to name Joseph A. Borkowski as Honorary President because of his work as a pioneer historian in the field of local history. In 1955 Borkowski was involved with the restoration of the monument honoring the soldiers buried on the grounds of what is now the Foster Community Center. Then in 1962 he successfully convinced the Dolly Madison Chapter of the U.S. Daughters of the Veterans of 1812 and other parties to save the historic cast, which commemorated the 100th anniversary of the founding of the Allegheny Arsenal, and return the cast iron plaque to the grounds of Arsenal Park.
Borkowski and other civic-minded men also saved 35 of the historic stones from the demolished Allegheny Arsenal gatehouse, and moved them to Arsenal Park. Then on July 4, 1965, through Borkowski's efforts a historic marker was erected on 40th Street to designate the site of the Allegheny Arsenal.
In 1989 Borkowski was still active with many organizations, including the Polish National Alliance, Polish Roman Catholic Union, Polish Falcons of America, District IV (he served as secretary for this organization for 26 years), Legion of Honor Silver Medal of the Polish Falcons, American Legion, Boys Club of Western Pennsylvania, County Commander of the V.F.W., and the Chairman of the Americanism Committee of Allegheny County.
Over the years, Borkowski received a number of awards, citations, and commendations from the American Pilots Association, V.F.W. Man of the Year, Allegheny County Bi-Centennial Heinz Foundation Medal, Arsenal Board of Trade Man of the Year, Polish Army Citation, Community Serve Award from the Boys and Girls Club of Western Pennsylvania, and the Service Award from the Catholic Diocesan Holy Name Union.
Borkowski's writings are scattered in various libraries and archives, and it is doubted that he ever bothered to catalog his works. The following constitutes a partial listing of his published writings:
"Early Polish Pioneers In The City of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County" (1948)
"The Lawrenceville Burial Ground and William B. Foster" (1955)
"City of Pittsburgh's Part in the Formation of the Polish Army – World War I 1917-1920" (1956)
"Camp Wilkins: Military Post 1861," Western Pennsylvania Historical Magazine, Vol. 45, September 1962.
"Pittsburgh and John Morgan," Pittsburgh Press, Sunday, July 31, 1963.
"Selected Highlights of Poland's History and of Polish American Historical Events," Pittsburgh, PA: Polish Falcons of America, 1968.
Historical Highlights and Sites of Lawrenceville Area (Comprising Present 2nd, 6th, 9th, and 10th Wards of the City of Pittsburgh), (1969).
"The Role of Pittsburgh's Polish Falcons in the Organization of the Polish Army in France," (1972).
The Poles of Erie (1972)
"Prominent Polish Pioneers of the United States of America, 1770-1790" (1975)
(With George Swetnam) "Our Military Heritage," Bicentennial Commission of Pittsburgh, (1976)
"Father Stanislaus Parzyk, C. P.," (Booklet) Memorial Service and Dedication and Unveiling of the Plaque to Rev. Stanislaus Parzyk, Pittsburgh: Sponsored by the Passionist Congregation and the Polish Historical Commission of the Central Council of Polish Organizations, December 4, 1977.
"History of the Central Council of Polish Organization in City of Pittsburgh, PA" (1980)
Miscellaneous History of Lawrenceville (1989)
"Holy Family Church 50 Years Ago, Fiftieth Anniversary of the Current Holy Family Church Building" Booklet, October 28, 1990.
"200th Anniversary of the Polish Constitution," Polish Day Anniversary Booklet at Kennywood (1991).
"History of the Legion of Honor," Sokol Polski, May 15, 1995.
Acquisition Information
Initial gift from Joseph Borkowski in 1965; additional material subsequently added.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Scope and Content Notes
Material documenting Polish Americans in western Pennsylvania collected by Joseph A. Borkowski.
Existence and Location of Copies
A digital reproduction of the last issue of the Pittsburczanin is available online (https://digital.library.pitt.edu/islandora/object/pitt:31735066257571).
Related Material
Alliance College Records, 1929-1976, AIS.1997.25, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Pennsylvania -- Emigration and immigration; Polish Americans -- Pennsylvania -- History; Societies; Polish Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Societies and clubs; Ethnic groups; Polish people -- Foreign countries -- History; Borkowski, Joseph A.
- Poles in the United States and Western Pennsylvania, I.
  Scope and Content Note
  Joseph Borkowski assembled a large collection of research documents about the Polish-American community in Western Pennsylvania. This series contains various materials about the history and culture of Polish-American communities in Western Pennsylvania and the surrounding states. Included is business correspondence between Joseph Borkowski and members of committees he held positions on. The subseries contains a large collection of documents about religious history within Pittsburgh and the surrounding area as well as Polish musicians in the early twentieth century. Also included are essays written by Joseph Borkowski based on research from this collection. Though the documents in this series are mainly about the Polish-American community, there are also documents and essays about the Croation, Slovakian, Slovenian, and Jewish communities in Pittsburgh and the surrounding area. The documents in this series are mostly newspaper articles and essays, as well as some books, correspondence, and government documents, and speeches. The douments in this series are in English and Polish.
  - Poland, Polish History, and Immigration, 1789-1990; 1956-1990; 1.
    This subseries contains various documents relating to the history of Poland and the Polish diaspora in the United States as well as Polish immigration to the United States. Many of the materials are books and essays about Polish history and culture. Also included are lists of Polish settlers in Western Pennsylvania and the history of immigration to the area in the eighteenth, nineteenth, and twentieth centuries. The materials about immigration also include three naturalization certificates from 1913, 1915, and 1922, as well as an immigrant handbook belonging to the person who was naturalized in 1922. The documents from the latter half of the twentieth century include correspondence and meeting materials about Polish-American efforts to raise relief funds for Poland in the 1960s, 1970s, and 1980s. The majority of this subseries is in English with a few documents in Polish.
    - About Poland: the Shattering of Myths, article, Chicago Tribune, September 2, 1973 (Folder 1)
    - Article on Polish Emigres, the New York Times, February 14, 1971 (Folder 2)
    - Bibliographies on Poland and Eastern Europe, 1933-1971 (Folder 3)
    - Borkowski Coat of Arms Historiography, no date (Folder 4)
    - Certificates of Citizenship and Immigrant Handbook, (Pittsburgh), 1913-1922 (Folder 5)
    - Coins of Poland, booklet, edited by Rev. John Suchos, 1920 (Folder 6)
    - Collection of Articles on Polish Heraldry, booklet, by Edward A. Peckwas, 1978 (Folder 7)
    - Correspondence about missing dates from book, December 17, 1967 (Folder 8)
    - Early Polish Pioneers in City of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, booklet, original and photocopy, 1948 (Folder 9)
    - European Nations and the Polish Insurrection of January 1863, article, no date (Folder 10)
    - Facts and Figures, The National Emblem, Colours, and Anthem of the Polish State, booklet by J. Tafelsk, no date (Folder 11)
    - Freedom of the Press in Poland, booklet, by M.E. Rojek, 1946 (Folder 12)
    - Genealogy Resources, reference booklets, c. 1970 (Folder 13)
    - God, Shield, Poland, placard, no date (Folder 14)
    - Immigration and the Ethnic Factor in American History, research grants, (University of Minnesota), 1975 (Folder 15)
    - In Memoriam, Sir Sigmund H. Uminski, April 3, 1975 (Folder 16)
    - Institute of Genealogy and Historical Research, correspondence, 1975 (Folder 17)
    - Lists of Polish Pioneers, (Western Pennsylvania), 1789-1924 (Folder 18)
    - Maps of Poland, celebrating the millennium of the state, 1960 (Folder 19)
    - Meeting of the Polish Diaspora Delegation, article, May 7 and 8, 1971 (Folder 20)
    - Migration to America, article, no date (Folder 21)
    - No 'Pallbearers' in Poland, article, no date (Folder 22)
    - Poland in the Collection of the Library of Congress, booklet, by Kazimierz Grzybowski, 1968 (Folder 23)
    - Poland Restores a Palace, article, the Washington Post, (Warsaw), February 8, 1971 (Folder 24)
    - Poland's National Flag and Emblem, booklet by John R. B. Szala, 1972 (Folder 25)
    - Poland's Youth Demand More Freedom, article, the Wanderer, February 11, 1971 (Folder 26)
    - Polish Constitution Day, Congressional Record, May 3, 1956 (Folder 27)
    - Polish Immigration to the United States, Professor Waclaw W. Soroka lecture notes (University of Wisconsin), 1983 (Folder 28)
    - Polish King Casimir Linked to all European Royalty, article, Polish-American Journal, September 1973 (Folder 29)
    - Polish National Hymn, songbook, no date (Folder 30)
    - Polish Pioneers of Pittsburgh and Polish Migration from Russian Poland, essay fragments, no date (Folder 31)
    - Polish-American Relief for Poland, meeting information and correspondence, 1964-1981 (Folder 32)
    - Polish-Czech Relations, book, Waclaw Lypacewicz, 1936 (Folder 33)
    - Red field – White Eagle: an Introduction to Polish Surnames, article and correspondence, 1972 (Folder 34)
    - Royal Order of Piast, book, no date (Folder 35)
    - Selection of Correspondence in the 20th Century Proposing a Slavic Commonwealth of Nations, booklet, 1973 (Folder 36)
    - Three Postcards from Warsaw, blank, no date (Folder 37)
    - Undelivered Letters, article, November 10, 1982 (Folder 38)
    - Voting Poster 1989, book, (Poland), 1990 (Folder 39)
  - Education, 1916-1996; 1960-1977; 2.
    This subseries contains documents relating to Polish-American educational institutions in Western Pennsylvania. A large portion of this material is about Alliance College, a higher education institution in Cambridge Springs, Pennsylvania operational between 1912 and 1988. The college was founded in order to promote the study of Polish language and culture in the United States. Also included is Ignacy Jan Paderewski's address to the first graduating class of 1916. The majority of the documents are booklets, books, and programs. Most of the documents are in English and some are in Polish.
    - Alliance College 50th Anniversary Dinner Program (Braddock, PA), 1962 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Alliance College Building Program (Cambridge Springs, PA), 1966 (Folder 41)
    - Alliance College Bulletins (Cambridge Springs, PA), 1925 - 1926 and 1951-1952 (Folder 42)
    - Alliance College Commencement Programs (Cambridge Springs, PA), 1971, 1972, and 1975 (Folder 43)
    - Alliance College Fundraising Letter (Cambridge Springs, PA), 1969 (Folder 44)
    - Alliance College Informational Booklets (Cambridge Springs, PA), 1969 (Folder 45)
    - Alliance College Kujawiaki, List of Members 1974/1975 (Cambridge Springs, PA), no date (Folder 46)
    - Central Catholic High School Anniversary book (Pittsburgh), 1977 (Folder 47)
    - Dinner Honoring Hon. John G. Brosky and Members of the Advisory Council, Alliance College program (Pittsburgh), 1966 (Folder 48)
    - Essay, History of the St. Stanislaus Parochial School, by Joseph Borkowski (Pittsburgh), no date (Folder 49)
    - Essay, The Parochial Schools, by Joseph Borkowski (Pittsburgh), no date (Folder 50)
    - Help Save Alliance College, flyer, (Cambridge Springs, PA), no date (Folder 51)
    - Immaculate Heart of Mary School 100th Anniversary booklet (Pittsburgh), 1996 (Folder 52)
    - Immaculate Heart of Mary School, Selected Historical Notes by Joseph Borkowski, no date (Folder 53)
    - Journal article from Georgia Historical Society, Madame Sophie Sosnowski, Educator of Young Ladies, by Mary Harriet White (Erie, PA), no date (Folder 54)
    - Lawrenceville Catholic School Merger (Pittsburgh), 1975 (Folder 55)
    - Paderewski's Address at the Second Annual Commencement of Alliance College (Cambridge Springs, PA), 1916 (Folder 56)
    - Parishioners oppose closing of St. Mary of Assumption School, newspaper clipping, The Pittsburgh Catholic, (Glenshaw, PA), February 18, 1971 (Folder 57)
    - Polish Intercollegiate Club, Programs and Newsletters (Pittsburgh), 1948-1949 (Folder 58)
    - St. John Kanty Preparatory School and College Anniversary Books (Erie, PA), 1937 and 1959 (Folder 59)
    - Szczecin University Choir USA Tour Program, 1995 (Folder 60)
  - Polish Community in Pittsburgh, 1887-1993; 1968-1981; 3.
    This subseries contains materials relating to the Polish-American community in Pittsburgh. The majority of the documents are about Polish Hill and to a lesser extent about Lawrenceville. Full copies of the Pittsburgh Press between 1956 and 1983 are included. These newspapers contain articles about the Polish-American community in Western Pennsylvania as well as articles about Polish and Polish-American history and culture. Also included is the service record of Thomas F. Ensight (1887 - 1917) who served in the United States Army during the First World War. This subseries mostly contains newspaper articles and letters to the editor. An essay by Joseph Borkowski based on research from this collection is also included. The majority of the documents are in English, very few are in Polish.
    - Anger in Polish Hill, newspaper article, Pittsburczanin, June 28, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Big Thunder on Polish Hill, newspaper article, Pittsburczanin, no date (Folder 62)
    - Certificate of Appreciation for Services Rendered to the Polish Community, given to Joseph Borkowski, August 25, 1968 (Folder 63)
    - Demographic Profile of Polish Hill, prepared by Sandy Smeltz, (Pittsburgh), no date (Folder 64)
    - Demography and Evolution of An Urban Ethnic Community: Polish Hill, Pittsburgh, article, American Journal of Physical Anthropology, July 1975 (Folder 65)
    - Ensight, Thos F., service record, photocopy, 1887-1917 (Folder 66)
    - Ethnicity in the Lawrenceville Area, essay by Joseph Borkowski, (Pittsburgh), no date (Folder 67)
    - Handsome House of Worship on Polish Hill Reflects Immigrants' Faith in God, (Pittsburgh), no date (Folder 68)
    - History becomes Homey, article, Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, (Pittsburgh), February 28, 1993 (Folder 69)
    - History of Poles in Pittsburgh, essay by Joseph Borkowski, no date (Folder 70)
    - Information on Pittsburgh Polonia, correspondence, no date (Folder 71)
    - Model City Redrawing Lines, article, (Pittsburgh), no date (Folder 72)
    - Pittsburgh City Council Resolution on Solidarity with Those of Polish Ancestry, December 24, 1981 (Folder 73)
    - Pittsburgh Press, (Pittsburgh), February 5, 1956 – December 4, 1983 (Folder 74)
    - Polish Hill Comeback: It Never Went Away, newspaper article, the Pittsburgh Press, (Pittsburgh), October 7, 1979 (Folder 75)
    - Polish Hill Rejects the Model City, newspaper article (Pittsburgh), July 19, 1968 (Folder 76)
    - Sympathy and Admiration to the Polish Hill, letter to the editor, (Pittsburgh), no date (Folder 77)
    - The Battle of Polish Hill Rages, newspaper article, the Pittsburgh Press, (Pittsburgh), August 18, 1968 (Folder 78)
    - The Environmental Inheritance, essay by Joseph Borkowski, (Lawrenceville), no date (Folder 79)
    - The Poles, article, Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, (Pittsburgh), May 23, 1982 (Folder 80)
    - The Poles, essay by Joseph Borkowski, (Pittsburgh), no date (Folder 81)
    - Tow. Ks. St. Staszyca Nest 69, 20th Anniversary book photocopy, (Polish Hill), 1926 (Folder 82)
  - Lawrenceville, 1969-1985; 4.
    This subseries contains information about the Lawrenceville neighborhood of Pittsburgh which does not directly relate to the Polish community in Pittsburgh. The neighborhood was founded in 1814 and incorporated into the city of Pittsburgh in 1868. The documents in this subseries are all from the twentieth century and mainly concern the history of Lawrenceville, the Lawrenceville Reviatalization Project, and community concerns in the 1960s, 1970s, and 1980s. A notable part of this subseries is the list of nickelodeons and theaters in Lawrenceville as well as a list of commonly used expressions in Lawrenceville. A history of Lawrenceville written by Joseph Borkowski based in part on research from this subseries is also included. All of the documents in this subseries are in English.
    - 50th Anniversary of American Legion Post no. 531, pamphlet, (Lawrenceville), June 6, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 83)
    - Anniversary of the First Settler in the Lawrenceville Area, essay by Joseph Borkowski, (Pittsburgh), no date (Folder 84)
    - Doughboy Square to be Rejuvenated, newspaper article, the Pittsburgh Press, (Lawrenceville), July 8, 1977 (Folder 85)
    - East Liberty Gazette, newspaper, (Pittsburgh), June 21, 1973 (Folder 86)
    - Expressions Commonly Used in the Lawrenceville Area, list by Joseph Borkowski, (Pittsburgh), no date (Folder 87)
    - Getting into Communities, journal article, the Pittsburgh Fair Witness, (Lawrenceville), 1971 (Folder 88)
    - Historical Highlights and Sites of the Lawrenceville Area, essay by Joseph Borkowski, (Pittsburgh), 1969 (Folder 89)
    - Lawrenceville Bicentennial Celebration, programs and newspaper clipping, (Pittsburgh), 1976 (Folder 90)
    - Lawrenceville Community Program, memorandum and job descriptions, (Pittsburgh), 1973 (Folder 91)
    - Lawrenceville Economic Action Program, Health and Social Service Committee Minutes, (Pittsburgh), no date (Folder 92)
    - Lawrenceville News, monthly newspaper, (Pittsburgh), 1982-1985 (Folder 93)
    - Lawrenceville Nickelodeons and Theaters, list, (Pittsburgh), no date (Folder 94)
    - Lawrenceville Planning Council, minutes, memoranda, and correspondence, (Pittsburgh), 1973-1975 (Folder 95)
    - Lawrenceville Views, newspaper and work schedule, (Pittsburgh), 1973-1974 (Folder 96)
    - Lawrenceville Wants Safety, Bypass, letter to the editor, the Pittsburgh Press, (Pittsburgh), October 3, 1973 (Folder 97)
    - Lawrenceville: An Historical Profile, essay by Joseph Borkowski, (Pittsburgh), no date (Folder 98)
    - Lawrenceville: Blue-Collar Neighborhood, information from 1970 US Census, prepared by Ruth Jones, (Pittsburgh), May 1973 (Folder 99)
    - Letter about Dedication for the Renaissance Federal Credit Union, (Pittsburgh), April 27, 1983 (Folder 100)
    - Petition to Continue the Arsenal Family and Children's Center, (University of Pittsburgh), 1974 (Folder 101)
    - Polish Hill – Lawrenceville Neighborhood Revitalization Project, correspondence, meeting minutes, and reports, (Pittsburgh), 1976-1977 (Folder 102)
    - Proposals for a Lawrenceville newspaper, (Pittsburgh), 1973 (Folder 103)
    - Scheduled meetings, organization unknown, (Pittsburgh), 1974 (Folder 104)
    - The Environmental Inheritance – Pittsburgh Area, Lawrenceville Section, essay by Joseph Borkowski, no date (Folder 105)
    - The History of Lawrenceville, book photocopy, (Pittsburgh), 1983 (Folder 106)
    - The Lawrenceville Burial Ground and William B. Foster, essay by Joseph Borkowski, (Pittsburgh), no date (Folder 107)
    - The Ninth Ward Withdraws, article, the Pittsburgh Catholic, (Lawrenceville), no date (Folder 108)
    - The Pittsburgh Press Roto, segment on Lawrenceville, (Pittsburgh), October 17, 1976 (Folder 109)
  - Culture and Heritage, 1868-1996; 5.